okay please give me 5 minutes to talk to
you about geography because we need to
understand the scale of what's going on
this is the state of North Carolina this
is the area that's without power still
this is also the state of North Carolina
this yellow outline is the country of
Belgium that I've overlaid for
scale
okay this is the scale 230,000 customers
without power means households based on
US Census Data the average household
size here is about three which means
we're talking about 6 to 700,000 people
who have not had power for a week that
is an emergency by itself if you don't
have power for a week then if you had
food stored in the freezer no you don't
if you had breast milk insulin stored in
the fridge no you don't you don't get to
run your CPAP machine 3/4 of a million
people without power for a
week should make Headline News by itself
but power outages are unfortunately one
of the mildest problems water is also
out cell coverage is out if you're
seeing people posting from this area
there's a good likelihood they're having
to drive miles to do that and that is if
they have a car that wasn't destroyed if
they can get gas somehow and if they
have roads they can drive miles on these
are the road
closures okay and these roads are not
closed because there's some water on
them they're closed because they look
like this
s right this times this
that's the scale the reason the roads
look like that is because this is the
topography this is not like a lot of
cities where you drive for a half an
hour to go get to this this is the
region this is where people live when
you live in the mountains you get one
road and they're going to put it
wherever they can put it that's why it's
shaped like this very often that's going
to be along a river or next to it when a
road looks like this right that means
the land looks like this so when a
hurricane decides to go hiking in the
mountains which has never happened in
this area before ever you're going to
get a torrential amount of water and
it's going to be moving very fast
because it's moving down a mountain and
this river is going to explode it's
going to take out this road right here
and it's going to take out this road
right here and then everybody that lives
in here is trapped because you're not
walking out some people are some people
are putting what they can and their
children on their back and Hiking out
which is to be honest pretty
representative of typical Appalachian
scrappiness anyway the other thing
that's going to happen is mud because
the water is not going to just gently
fall down the mountain and go in the
river it is going to get into the Earth
and the Earth is going to become mud and
that is incredibly heavy and the whole
mountain side is going to Shear off like
a windshield wiper and carry everything
with it and put it in the river and
that's why we're seeing the level of
Destruction we're seeing because roads
are not the only thing that is gone this
is not a river this is a
town this is Chimney Rock This is a
screenshot from this user this is what
it looked like
before and this is the scale that we're
talking about there are hundreds of
small towns in this picture this is
Asheville this right here you've heard a
lot about Asheville probably hopefully
Asheville is not a small remote Mountain
Town it is a city of 100,000 people it
is the city that you would drive to to
go to the doctor if you live in an
actual small remot mountain town and it
did get devastated it did get hit very
hard but part of the reason why you are
seeing so much coverage out of Asheville
is that you can get there right now if
you're going to send a news crew to
North Carolina they can just drive into
Asheville and you do not want to be
taking up a helicopter right now just to
take pictures because people are still
trapped I do think some news
organizations went here for a working
lunch and didn't ask anybody if anyone
lives up here so I'm a little frustrated
by that but gradually I think the
coverage is developing um the rest of
this is going to be very Bleak so don't
watch it if you're already not okay
please the mortality counts that you've
seen in the tens are irresponsibly
optimistic those are the people who've
been identified when you find someone's
remains washed down a river how do you
know where they came from how do you
contact their loved ones to get an
identification when the cell towers are
down when the roads are down when all of
those people are still concentrating on
trying to get out and trying to get food
and water you're you're going to wait
you're going to wait until the living
are taken care of we have not begun to
hear the mortality numbers from this
disaster this is a small
country and it's my mom's small
country and it's
gone please pay attention